howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
listeners have asked us provide pointers
some of the resources we talked about on
the show we now have links to books and
articles referenced in recent podcasts
that are available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
ruts show com that's Jim ruts show com
today's guest is Michael Moe Goosen of
Blue Mountain capital hm hi doing doing
great how about you I'm great thank you
great to have you
prior to joining blue mountain Michael
was head of global financial strategies
at Credit Suisse and chief investment
strategist at Legg Mason Capital
Management I know Michael from the Santa
Fe Institute where he's been a longtime
stalwart supporter and for the last
seven years been the chairman of our
board of trustees he's the author of one
of the best books on investing more than
you know finding financial wisdom in
unconventional places and he has a new
book out the success equation untangling
skill and luck in business sports and
investing which we'll get to soon but
first Michael could you tell our
audience have been about the Santa Fe
Institute what you find a value there
for your work and for your life well
first off Jim you didn't mention this
but of course I took over I filled your
very big shoes as chairman of the board
and you know it is an institute that's
founded about 35 years ago by a number
of scientists who felt that academia had
become too siloed and that many of the
vexing important issues in the world
stood at the intersection of disciplines
so it's a non-degree conferring
institute that works on basic research
questions across disciplines and the
unifying theme if there is one is is
complex system so interactions of lots
of little agents and what emerges from
that and how those things evolve over
time you know my introduction to SFI was
through bill Miller and it was a very
one of these very specific moments I
recall we were at a baseball game and I
had a beer in one hand and a hotdog in
another and Bill said you know there's
this place out of New Mexico you ought
to check out I was I was a financial
analyst and I was reading a lot of stuff
and in science and biology evolution all
this kind of stuff and so that
encouraged me to go out there probably a
little over close to 25 years ago
and I was immediately enthralled just
some of the presentations the way of
thinking and I think for me one of the
most extraordinary values of the
Institute is just the fact that it has a
lot of it draws people who are actively
open-minded Oh intellectually curious
people so yeah it's a it's a neat place
and I think often people in the business
world or finance world feel like some of
the ideas or themes are not that
applicable to business or investing but
if you hang around a little bit and have
an open mind
they're just enormous number of
connections between all the business in
the world of investing and the study of
complex systems so it's not only been
personally very gratifying and the
source of great growth but also
professionally actually really
interesting and valuable yeah indeed I
should say it's been an unfair weapon
for me ever since I got involved in and
you know to the point of applicability
one of the points I like to make to
people is that yes sometimes the actual
science hard core may be a little
difficult to apply but the metaphors
that come out of it are unbelievable
things like you know Fitness landscapes
increasing returns the scale etc that
are somewhat different than the
conventional way of looking at the world
are extraordinarily powerful lenses for
thinking about both business and
investing I agree with that a hundred
percent and the way I think about not
not just in business or investing but
just life is that it's really good to
try to build a toolbox of tools so that
when you face a problem you have the
right tool in this case perhaps picking
up on what you said a metaphor to try to
solve that or think about it effectively
and so I think one of the joys of life's
although it's a bit of work is its to
constantly working on your toolbox and
thinking about different ways of
approaching problems and I would just
say that associating with s Fi and the
folks there is just a great way to help
build out that toolbox and again very
intellectually fulfilling but but
actually very practical as well indeed
now before we hop into talking about
your book at all I'm sure our audience
would also appreciate a little insight
into your day job as a value investor in
prepping for the podcast I happened upon
a really interesting document your room
titled who is on the other side it's 51
pages and we'll put a link to it up on
the website and it's well worth reading
I thought that was just an amazing
perspective on investing because you
condense your perspective down to a few
minutes yeah sure I mean and by the way
and I also teach at Columbia Business
School as an adjunct so I'm a pretend
professor but it's been great and I
teach the course in a number of
different modules one of the modules is
thinking about why to markets mispriced
securities and this is something over
the years Jim that I typically
pontificate about but really had done
very little to codify my thinking so I'm
like all right after all these years
maybe I should sit down and actually get
serious about this and try to quantify
this the title I saw from another
presentation who's on the other side but
you know this is also if you're if
you're a poker player which I know that
you are at least happened in the past
you know when you're up against somebody
you want to think about what does that
other person thinking what do they have
in their hand how they approaching the
world it's very much true for investing
when you put on a trade you buy or sell
something the question you should be
asking yourself is what do I know or
where I think I know that this person
doesn't and why they motivate to do
something on the opposite side of my
trade so when I try to try to break this
down there are four potential areas of
mispricing
the first is you know we call it
behavioural but that you know basically
were social beings and and investing is
inherently a social exercise and from
time to time we sort of correlate our
behaviors and lead to sort of excesses
and markets or the theme of over
extrapolation so behavioral that I mean
there are a lot of other subsets but
that's a big one the other ones
analytical so you and I have the SAC
same information but we analyze it in
different ways or come to different
conclusions you can imagine how that
would work as well the third one is
informational which is the most obvious
is that you know something that I don't
know or vice-versa
of course governments around the world
that try to encourage companies to
disclose information uniformly and this
low-cost as possible
to sort of get rid of that advantage but
there certainly have to be informational
advantages as well and and by the way
even part of that is there's a huge
literature on what we pay attention to
so it's not so much the information is
not out there we just don't wait it all
the same way and then the final one is
technical which is some
people have to buy or sell for reasons
that have nothing to do with
fundamentals you know you have to pay
your kids college tuition you're gonna
sell just because you need to raise the
cash to pay the tuition and has nothing
to do or there's no statement about the
values at all so I just try to create
this sort of comprehensive framework and
say every time you put on a trade and
you think you're gonna you're gonna
generate an excess return just give some
thought as to who's on the other side of
that and why you think specifically you
have some sort of an edge and you know I
just think it's a really rich way to
think about things versus just think in
your head you're the most clever person
walking around it and if you've been in
markets by the way for any period of
time and you're not humble about it then
then something's wrong I mean markets
are the most humbling mechanism I can
imagine yeah I can tell you the same
experience over my 35 years or so and
you know and you know to your point you
know nothing drives me crazy er than
hearing two morons at a restaurant
discussing the tip they got from their
broker as if this was God's own truth
exactly you're human so it's all
entertaining right so we love stories
and and we'd love to defer to experts
we'd love to defer to people who are in
quotes in the know but yeah we can just
know in real life that doesn't work out
so well
yeah in fact we'll finish this section
by a quote that you had in the paper
from I guess is your hero Benjamin
Graham he said have the courage of your
knowledge and experience if you have
formed a conclusion from the facts that
if he know your judgment is sound act on
it even though others may hesitate or
differ you are neither right nor wrong
because the crowd disagrees with you you
are right because your data and
reasoning are right beautiful right and
you know it's interesting that it the
course that I teach at Columbia Business
School is actually sort of the same
course at Ben Graham started teaching in
the 1920s so it's been around and at
Columbia for many many years and I think
that you know if you read Graham's work
you know security analysis from 1934 in
the intelligent investor
it's replete with examples that were at
the time contemporary but they feel very
dated and so and a lot of his methods
actually today and I think come across
as very dated but Graham's overarching
lesson to all of us is really about
temperament and philosophy of how you
approach in bed
in general and that quote I think really
embodies something that will ultimately
be timeless right which is people may go
bonkers but when the facts and you've
done the work and the facts in your
judgement align to suggest you should do
something you should just go ahead with
with some conviction so a lot of that is
the thing the lasting lesson of Ben
Graham is really about temperament and
how you approach this philosophically
and that is that's a powerful thing that
we will talk about another 100 years
from now I think and we'll talk about
things related to it as we talk about
your book so now let's turn to the 6x
Equation untangling skill and locked-in
business sports and investing I knew
this is going to be interesting when
right up front I saw that you had said
if you are the underdog you want to
inject luck by making the game more
complex this is the rule I've long found
useful but yet does not seem to be
something that most people intuitively
know for example chess I'm a mediocre
real world chess player but a pretty
decent barroom chess player and mostly
because I when I discover my opponent is
better than me which is fairly often
I just relentlessly raise the complexity
of the middle game and most people don't
take that strategy I've got some other
examples from business but why don't you
tell us your perspective on that make
the game more complex when you're the
underdog yeah I mean that's awesome Jim
and I'll just say let me make this a
specific Santa Fe Institute connection
as well part of the motivation or the
insight on that came from a conversation
one day with Scott page yeah now at the
University of Michigan and Scott taught
me about this thing called the kernel
blotto game which I had never had never
heard of and for those that are not
initiated with Colonel blotto it was
developed by a mathematician back in the
1920s it's it's a segment of game theory
and actually was quite popular ran
Institute in the 1950s now if you talk
about game theory everyone's heard of
the prisoner's dilemma almost no one's
heard of Colonel blotto part of it
because the math was really difficult
and then I don't know 15 20 years ago a
young academic named Brian Robert
Robertson came along and mathematize the
Colonel blotto game so let me describe
what as so he developed this and this is
sort of where that would this let this
inside
so let me just drive the Colonel blotto
game very simply the setup is you have
you allocate two parties in number of
soldiers so Jim and I you'll not play so
I'll give you a hundred soldiers and
I'll have a hundred soldiers and then
we'll have three we specify number of
battlefield so it's called three
battlefields to start in the initial
condition and so what we do again we do
this independently in in blindly is we
allocate soldiers to each battlefield
then we sort of lift the veil and then
whoever has the most soldiers per
battlefield wins that battle and whoever
wins the most battles wins the war right
so that's the basic setup and the way I
just described 100 soldiers hundred
soldiers three battlefields that's
basically rock-paper-scissors right
there are some dumb strategies but but
most strategies it's just going to be a
cycle sort of cycle win-loss so that's
the basic setup but where Colonel blotto
gets really interesting is when you
change when you have asymmetry in the
number soldiers so now I give you a
hundred and fifty soldiers I have a
hundred there's still ways for me to win
but obviously many fewer and then the
second thing is to expand the number of
battlefields and that's where
Robertson's stuff got really really
interesting because it turns out that in
an asymmetric battle the way you dilute
the strength of the stronger player is
to increase the number of battlefields
or ie to add complexity to it right as
you as you sort of let me add luck but
just add complexity as you mentioned in
the middle game in chess and so this is
this really fascinating idea that when
you're the stronger player what you want
to do is simplify the game right because
then your skill or your strength will
overwhelm your competitor and if you're
the underdog you want to come make the
game more complex now in the business
world we would talk about things like
disruptive innovation the work by clay
Christensen a disruptive innovation sort
of a classic approach to sort of taking
a weird approach to trying to compete
not going toe-to-toe with the incumbent
but rather sort of competing on the
edges again making the income and do
something they're not comfortable doing
or they are not interested in doing or
they're not incentivized to doing okay
Jim can I also mention something weird
that I think you're gonna really like by
the way I have at it
others I don't think we've talked about
this directly but there's a really
interesting book by Roy boom
called is there anything good about men
do you know this book do not okay this
is gonna be up your alley and so beau
Meister starts with us you know it's
this thing about by the way is there
anything good about men people often
joke it's gonna be a pretty short short
book but but as actually his point is
they're actually he's just you know men
and women are different for a lot of
interesting reasons but there's a
chapter in there this particular
interest in when he talks about what so
one of the observations we know just in
life is that men and women in most
things the averages are about the same
right and this aside personality stuff
and cognitive stuff and so forth but we
also know that by from many many things
the variance of men is higher than the
variance of women right so there are
more men on the right tail and more men
in the left tail even if the average is
the same
yeah but the comprehensive social
science result pretty much correct and
so beau Meister asked to sort a question
like why is that that's not a sort of
weird thing so one of his chapters he
opens and he says let me ask you a
really simple question if you think back
to all of our ancestors what percent
were women and what percent were men and
your intuitive answer is well everyone
has a mother and a father so it should
be 50/50 and if you you know where I'm
going with this the answer is that's not
at all the case and this is based on
genetics and no one really knows the
exact number but the ratios something
like two-to-one women to men so in other
words and let's just call it two thirds
of all ancestors or women and one-third
of ancestors or men so saying this
differently in the sweep of human
history and by the way don't look at
just humans look at any other primates
or any other mammals in general it's the
case that women have a roughly twice the
probability of reproducing than men do
so for the vast part of human history
most men were reproductive dead ends and
a few men actually reproduced a ton so
once you could think about this is model
this actually as an option right like a
financial option right we're above a
certain strike price you're in the money
and below that your blows out of the
money and if you want an option to be
valuable how do you do that and the
answer is increase the volatility uh-huh
right so isn't this interesting as an
issue in connection ah I love this I do
it's give you up your alley right
the argument is something along the
lines of mother nature says well we know
that most males are not going to
reproduce forget about the contemporary
world but going back over time most
meals are not going to reproduce so the
strategy from a female's point of view
is reduce variants and you know you're
pretty much going to be in the money for
a male it's like hey you're probably not
going to be in the money so increase
variants so again every time there's a
conversation about they're too many men
on the right side of the distribution
you should first question should be what
about the left side of the distribution
and check that out and there are even
interesting things I mean I think a
little bit more speculative but you know
the math SATs that boys do better than
girls on average by a number of points
but the reason the conjecture is the
reason is about 150 or 200 thousand
fewer boys take the SAT than girls and
the speculation is though boys that
don't take the SAT or the left tail and
if they were compelled to take it they
would fill in the left tail the mean
would shift right in line and we have
the same distribution we see everywhere
else so anyway so this is an interesting
idea so so I think not only is this a
cool idea from the world the point of
view a business right and as you pointed
out in just a strategy or are you
playing chess but it's also mother
nature figured this out and incra I
think I think one of the reasons we have
high variability is because that's the
way you get a higher likelihood of being
in the money with an option yeah right
how's that how's that for a great idea
and that's great it's a perfect setup
cuz I have a note here that says that
beyond raising the complexity I'm very
closely related corollary is when you're
behind raise the variance right similar
not quite the same thing and you know
just a couple of factual items some
mammals are way more asymmetrical and a
reproduction and even historical humans
white-tailed deer both the deer hunter
and I use them as my model species on my
theories of conscious cognition they're
about 6x only about one in six males
reproduces and of course we've all heard
the story of Genghis Khan supposedly
twenty-five percent of the people in
Central Asia are descended from him so
even in humans the numbers can be more
asymmetric right and by the way I'll
just say that Bo meister speculum by the
way a lot of this I think is
you know I think it makes sense but it's
somewhat speculative but Bo Meister
speculates that the ratio is much higher
for humans as well and some of our more
contemporary social mechanisms have
narrowed the gap between men and women
so so I don't know if we were ever
white-tailed deer territory but you know
and again look at other primates you see
very similar things and again there's
within even what there's a lot of
differences within for example primates
or other other mammals but the basic
setup is pretty widely seen in nature
yeah there's actually a wonderful
historical example from US history which
is the Civil War
all right the South was behind
positionally industrially manpower wise
all kinds of ways but they had better
generals for least for the first part of
the war and those generals particularly
realized the only chance he had was to
raise the variance
hence the battles of Antietam and
Gettysburg where Lee took big huge risk
and tried to end the war with a big roll
of dice it turned out that it wasn't
quite successful but at least he had a
chance and when the Union tried to match
him smart play for smart play they
weren't successful but when they got a
guy who saw the biggest picture of all
grant and realized his job was to not
lose essentially lower the variance he
gradually just squeezed the south until
it collapsed so there's a perfect
example of both sides of I will
mentioned you might jump in that there's
actually a whole book about asymmetric
warfare which is fascinating and this
guy looked at asymmetric warfare going
back 200 years and broke it into like 50
year blocks and what he found was that
in ancient days and by the way it's a
really interesting thing why is that
ancient days couple hundred years ago a
lot of warfare it was less about
actually winning and more about honor so
you know if you went off to war you were
there to serve your country and honor
your family and so people you know so
they would go toe-to-toe with the the
stronger thing and just get blasted and
then then people start realize if we
want to win we need to increase variants
and do weird things all these things
like guerrilla tactics you mentions were
these different techniques from the
southern generals and so there so this
guy actually documented a 200 year sweep
of asymmetric warfare and again it fits
beautifully with a Colonel blotto stuff
but if it's
what that what you just described by the
way it's an entry in question why have
Wars been predominantly in fact anything
risky why they predominately send men to
do those things
exploration why he sent men and not
women the answer is because men are
expendable right if you don't need that
many of them to propagate the species
they're expendable so send them off to
do all the dirty jobs right anyway it so
it's very interesting stuff I was at the
book how the week wind wars by argument
off very good man yes it is that's the
book and back to the you know the
ability making men expendable there's a
famous quote by Napoleon after a big
loss in one of his battles he said was
he concerned about the long-term history
of France because of these big losses
and he puffed himself up and said my
soldiers will replace the losses tonight
[Laughter]
that's a good one so let's get back to
the mainstream of what you're talking
about the book you know sort of at the
very core of it is the difference
between skill and luck maybe you could
start with describing what those two
things are and what you mean by the
skill and luck in the rest of the book
exactly and I'll just say that um I
think that there are a lot of aphorisms
about luck you know luck is where
success meets opportunity or preparation
meets opportunity and the harder I work
the luckier I get things like that
actually think a lot of those things
they have a good sentiment which is I
kind of work hard but they're very Mis
founded I think so let me let's just
take a moment to define both of these
things first I would define skill right
out of the dictionary right which is the
ability to apply one's knowledge readily
in execution or performance right so you
know how to do something and when you're
asked to do it you can do it on cue so
you could think about a musician or an
athlete or something like that luck is
much more difficult to define and by the
way this gets right into philosophy you
almost have to put a stake in the ground
to sort of limit the discussion Nick
rush pressure a professor of philosophy
at University of Pittsburgh wrote a book
about luck and I I sort of liked his
definition so he said luck exists when
three conditions are in place one is it
happens to an individual or an
organization so you can you can sort of
figure out the unit to which it happens
second it could be good or bad and I
don't mean to leave anybody the
impression
it's symmetrical because it's certainly
not we can talk more about that in a few
moments but there is such a thing as
good luck or bad luck and by the way
even if you look at the etymology words
related to Locke's things like fortune
and chance many of them don't have
asymmetry luck I think would and the
final thing in this is a trickiest one
is it's reasonable to expect a different
outcome could have occurred so for you
rewind the tape of time and you play it
again it is reasonable to expect a
different outcome could occur so those
are that does that those I think are the
basic definitions and I think Jim if you
sort of try to get to the core of this
book there's one illustration I think
it's easy for people to do it mentally
as well is I call it the luck skill
continuum so you can imagine a Content
just a straight line on the far left
we'll call it all luck no skill
so activities where skill plays no role
whatsoever in your success and you know
things like lotteries farewell roulette
wheel those would be examples of that on
the far right would be pure skill no
luck or luck has no effect whatsoever
and again nothing's perfect over there
but it would be things like running
races or swimming races or chess is
probably close to that side of the
spectrum as well and then the the key is
that almost everything in life is
between those two extremes and the
question is where is your activity and
where does it find itself on that luck
skill continuum and then from there
spill out the kinds of strategies or
approaches you should take to thinking
about how to approach that particular
activity in the way that's most
effective as possible so that's that's
the basic set up like what is luck what
is skill and by the way by definition
this idea that you can create your own
luck if you accept what I just said
that's just not true right there's
anything you can do to improve your
likelihood of success that by definition
is skill right that's something within
your control so it goes back to same
thing I think the aphorisms about luck
are often encouraging people to work
hard or prepare and those are all good
sentiments but they don't really pass a
test if you think about defining these
things with even with a modicum of rigor
I will talk about this a little bit
later but my own life and I used to have
a presentation I gave the second year
MBA students called my famous career
where I pointed out that probably 60% of
my successes that were due to luck but I
also did point out that I was prepared
to take advantage of my luck in certain
ways the example I gave specially second
year MBA students was I always
maintained myself and my wife being
debt-free or as close to it as we could
with money in the bank even we were
young and poor so that when opportunity
came up we could just hop on it and
again and again and again that non being
nailed down was interacted with luck in
a very interesting way so you know you
had five or six pieces of luck in your
life why people couldn't have taken
advantage of them because they were over
committed somewhere else
and so I think you can manage your
interaction with luck yeah I agree with
that and I would just say this that that
here's another even more fundamental
thing which is to say will say you know
will describe skills what's in your
control versus what's not in your
control and will say luck is what's not
in your control so very much to your
point you're saying hey I my skill was
making sure that things that were in my
control were good right so I thought I
was financially flexible that kept
building my mind and making myself
learning every single day to make myself
more valuable in the workplace and so
forth and then when some opportunity
presented itself that was out of my
control I was in a position to take
advantage of it right so I think that
all hangs together reasonably well and
like you said the Society of being
prepared or this idea of having it's
almost I would say it's in your control
so enhance it it would fall at least by
my definition as as a skill I like that
this could be semantics it could be
semantics but yeah I think I I think I
think we're yeah I think we're saying
something very similar
I like that up I will frame that as the
skill of taking advantage of luck right
SEC and of course that's what poker is
right 100% to a significant degree right
at least in the short term long term
it's just skill but in the short term
it's taking advantage of luck
appropriately when it shows up so let's
turn now to the very interesting part of
the book and probably the one that a lot
of people gonna find most useful which
are
practical ways to disentangle skill
versus luck which people aren't
necessarily very good at yeah so well I
mean I would just say that it's
different in different things so I will
say that and we have a chapter we
dedicate to sort of asking questions
doing this but the most formal way to do
this there's actually a really beautiful
little theorem in statistics which says
that the variance of distribution
independent distribution a plus the
variance of distribution independent
distribution B equals the variance of a
plus B so it's a it's a really nice
little property and that's the main
thing we use to try to codify this for
example in sports so I just use as
sports so what's going on here well how
do you do this so let's just pick a
sport just a big basketball for instance
so the and the NBA they play 82 games
and so you have this equation and you
say well how can we sort it out
well variance of luck is something we
would know that's a it's a modification
of a binomial model right so you
basically say let's model out if every
game was decided by a coin toss how
would that look in terms of a
distribution so that's not that
difficult to do mathematically and that
gives me one of my first variances the
second thing we have is the actual
empirical results we actually know the
win-loss records of teams over time we
usually do multiple seasons to take out
some of the noise and so we have two of
the components of the equation right so
you have variance of what look like and
luck we have the actual results and the
way to plug the gap is to say what is
the variance of skill that solves for
that so I think that's one of the
classic techniques to do that when you
have data that are that are really clean
I'll leave it at that that and that's a
really good clean way to think about
disentangling luck and skill especially
in activities that are sort of clean
like that very good and then at a higher
level you talk about and the seem to
leaves two by two matrix maybe you could
talk about that a little bit yeah so I
think that not seems point is that the
kind of thing I just described is very
well suited to well-behaved
distributions right so normal
distributions win losses of basketball
teams and even to some degree things
like the results of businesses or
investors or so forth but where it
really breaks down are these district
that are very fat-tailed so where we
have these very infrequent but very
large effects so my argument is so so
this a lot of stuff on luck and skill
doesn't really do that much doesn't have
that much to say about those fat tail
distribution parts of the world that
said there's so much here that is
untapped just in the regular world right
the more bit better behaved parts of the
world that it's still incredibly
relevant so my my whole thing on luck
and skill is that I think very few
people think enough about it and
certainly in a sort of rigorous way and
that it has applications to large
swathes of the world but just to be
super clear that this sort of Nassim
Taleb fat-tailed component it's going to
be much less relevant to the plight
there and and again there are lots of
fads tailed things we could talk about
this a bit too like in the world of
physical worlds like earthquakes and so
forth I'm talking mostly about social
things so for example we and we could
talk a little bit about this but how do
when we think about things like
successes of movies or successes like
books those are almost impossible things
to model because of the way the social
dynamics unfold yeah also in the social
world wars tend to be fat-tailed
revolutions and probably even financial
crises so you know there is you know I
do think it's worth considering fat
tails as they insert themselves into our
real world for sure I want to draw
attention to it I completely agree with
you said I want to draw attention to the
idea and just say that that may be
beyond the purview of what we can really
do with these sets of tools but maybe
this actually would not be a bad time to
talk a bit about this which is and this
also through for me was a very Santa Fe
Institute influenced set of ideas but
when we talk about the nature of luck
there's sort of two different ways to
think about one are things that are
largely independent so these are you
know coin tosses or even if you model
like baseball players batting averages
and so forth they're not perfectly
independent processes but for the most
part that's a pretty good way to think
about it and they'll get you pretty
close to the truth but most of the
interesting things are many of the
interesting is in life are these social
processes right where it's these
cumulative processes and it's basically
how information propagates across a net
and those things are inherently very
difficult to predict and so as you as
you know well predictions of which books
will succeed which songs will be popular
which movies will be blockbusters
it's just inherently difficult known to
be inherently difficult so there was one
there was one experiment that was done
by one of our former postdocs Duncan
Watts he did it with Matt so again they
competed odds called Music Lab where
they they they basically got college
students and this is thousands of
college students and they asked him to
look at songs by unknown bands just just
under fifty songs by unknown bands and
they did something super interesting
which was they had a control which is
20% of population and then the other 10%
each went into eight social world so you
could think about these almost literally
as alternate universes and so they said
listen to the songs and rate them you
know love it or hate it and then if you
really like the song you can download it
so this is just that you know tell us
about your musical tastes and in one of
the extreme versions by the way they
showed a leaderboard so one of the most
liked songs were the most downloaded
songs and what they found was that the
control was that obviously a sense of
some sort of encouraged objective
assessment of the songs but what they
found was the pattern of how people
liked and downloaded songs was
extraordinarily important so just to be
clear the bad songs really did well in
the social worlds but if you were sort
of in the top third like kind of
anything could happen and there was one
particular song I thought really
captured the whole experiment perfectly
and the independent condition it was
smack dab in the middle so just consider
a completely average song in one of the
social worlds it was the number one hit
and another one of the social worlds it
was at the very bottom decile terms of
popularity so it just goes to show that
if you rewound the tape of time and
played it again you know ask the
question would Madonna be Madonna what
star wars beat star wars with Harry
Potter be Harry Potter and the answer is
highly highly unlikely and that leads to
another component that's worth
mentioning in all this which is we are
all storytellers right we are all
masters at creating narratives to
explain things after the fact so now
that something becomes popular we all
create a set of narratives to explain
why it became pop
there even though we are clueless about
the underlying mechanisms so that to me
is one of the most fascinating
components this thing I'm luck and again
very close tie back to SFI and how again
information propagating across network
is that you just have to be very very
circumspect about your assessment of
what has done well in a social realm and
of course anticipating what will do well
in a social realm as well and so that to
me was a really a big eye-opener you
mentioned things like markets and I
think that you could almost use the same
kind of model like propagation of
information across Network to understand
how booms and crashes happen right they
sort of fat tail events so super super
interesting stuff and you know even if
you don't know that as you as you point
out the very out outside even if you
don't know the details of how these
models work appreciation the very core
idea itself is incredibly valuable the
yeah that Music Lab result was amazing
and it confirmed one of my personal
biases which is I hate to invest in
those kinds of idiosyncratic pop culture
type things for instance you know even
though I did it once mostly just to
learn how to do it
the idea of betting on movies doesn't
appeal to me in the slightest while
betting on studios might be reasonable
right because your movie might be great
and doesn't succeed for a whole bunch of
reasons that have nothing to do with the
innate quality of the movie and that's
just not the kind of thing I personally
like to do and although obviously there
are people who do it know how successful
they are that's another question much
better to you know to own a studio and
have a portfolio and maybe you're better
on average making movies and then the
other point I want to hop on you
mentioned narrative and anyone who's
listened to the show has known that we
quite often talk about the power of
narrative and had various people bring
their perspectives on it and it is you
know as you started to allude to try to
get you'll go a little further it's the
source of a you know a fair number of
human biases and I'm particularly
interested in the route neuroscience of
it you know Mike Gazzaniga is split
brain studies with your reference in the
book where when you separate the right
brain from the left brain if you provide
something to the side of the brain that
can't see it
if it's the left brain which is the
verbal part it'll make up total
to try to make sense of what it
unconsciously knows so maybe you can
talk a little bit about how narrative is
a great source of cognitive bias
definitely so let me let me mention one
thing maybe we can put this in the notes
to that on the website for the success
equation we have a little poly or urn
model and and this is a really good way
for people to play around this concept
and almost like to train their
intuitions a bit about it and the way
the model is set up is we have Mart and
you can specify this conditions as you
as you see fit but we have marbles of
different colors five black marbles four
green marbles three red marbles and so
forth and then that's a pull and replace
model so what the simulation does is it
blindly pulls one of the models and of
the marbles and obviously there's going
to be a probability of that happening
and then matches it with a marble the
same color and puts it back in and does
the same thing over and over so the
reason I did that way is the initial
number of marbles is a proxy for skill
in quotation marks right and then that
process itself ends up being where the
luck comes in so if the draw is
obviously a probabilistic draw and I
think one of the big lessons from that
Jim just trying to riff on something you
mentioned a moment ago is that at a
certain point you get locking in these
processes right so so clearly the most
popular marvel gets picked and replaced
then the probability of succeeding goes
up but but you do get locked in after a
certain number of sessions so that's a
really interesting thing that even
things where there is varying skill and
that's why it's fun to play the
simulation because you can do it a
zillion times and see like when do the
low skill things become the most popular
and so forth
um this stuff on Gazzaniga and the
interpreter I love all this stuff and
you're exactly right just a transition
into that a bit and I think you
described it incredibly well I mean
Michael Gazzaniga is a neuroscientist
who did work on split brain patients and
these are people who have to live
debilitating epilepsy they failed all
their treatments and those last-ditch
effort they sever the corpus callosum so
very much to your point out by the way
the people do much better after this
right they feel much better and and it
relieves that the symptoms that seizures
going from one hemisphere to the other
but it sets up this incredibly
interesting experimental condition and
modularity and that you described it
extremely well
you can give a cue to the right
hemisphere with your left eye and the
person we reacted
you ask them why they're doing it and
they just make up a complete story right
because the left brain is where your
language resides so they call this part
of your brain in your left hemisphere
the interpreter and the job of the
interpreter is to close cause and effect
loops so I throw some effect at you I
throw some sort of an outcome of you and
you are going to come up with a
narrative to explain why that thing
happened and we all do it effortlessly
and naturally when you're read it in the
split brain literature it's actually as
you point out very humorous like people
come up with these crazy stories to
explain what's going on
but the key more sobering point is the
interpreters working in all of our
brains all the time the vast majority of
time very benignly but of course we're
making up stories for things that make
no sense whatsoever now here's the key
for me is that the interpreter doesn't
know about luck so typically when you
see a good outcome your brain is going
to come up with a narrative to explain
things that there's something good
behind it and when you see a bad outcome
you assume that something bad is behind
it and this is where it gets into a very
fundamental issue of process versus
outcome so I mentioned one of the biases
that's a very powerful one is this idea
called outcome bias is that we tend to
think that bad outcomes are consequence
of bad decisions which is not always the
case where good outcomes are the
consequence of good decisions and that's
clearly not the case so outcome bias is
a huge one you mentioned I know you're
you have an affinity for poker you
mentioned poker a few moments ago Annie
Duke and her book thinking in bets calls
this resulting so she claims that sort
of the poker version of this outcome
bias and that's a really really bad
habit to get into and that leads to
another point at least along luck skill
thing so when you are looking at when
you're in the lexical continuum if
you're on the skill side you don't need
a lot of sample size to know that
there's it's behind process right so if
you and I run a race you know the faster
guy is going to win the foot race and we
don't have to speculate about you know
whether there was that it's skill or
something else by contrast if you move
over to luck sided continuum it's all
about process and outcomes are very
misleading because there's a lot of
noise or luck that's distorting the
actual signal in those kinds of
situations so that's another thing is to
say when you're on the luck side of the
continuum where again skill plays a role
over
time but that the short term the skill
to signal-to-noise ratio is relatively
low you need to focus on process and
that's where this outcome buys and
that's where the interpreter becomes a
really really problematic thing because
you're gonna start to make associations
that are unfair to make and buy this is
pervasive I mean this is all the time in
sports where a coach will make a
decision that's the right decision but
doesn't work out it works it happens in
business all the time happens and
investing all the time so the the whole
Gazzaniga stuff on left hemisphere
interpreter incredibly important for
people understand by the way Bob shows
got a brand new book out called
narrative economics I think we talked
about this the Santa Fe Institute
symposium a couple weeks ago and that's
a whole book that just dedicated this
idea of how NER it is come to the
forefront demand our attention for some
period of time and lead to certain
actions it may or may not make any sense
so I think this is an incredibly
important thing in a really crucial
component to this whole discussion about
luck and skill and outcomes that we see
in the world yeah very good i fact that
Schiller's books on my stack soon to be
read and then you're absolutely right
outcome bias if you're not subject to it
is a wonderful tool in the poker world
or hey you see i'm full hit on you know
a bad decision
and he thinks that's wonderful for him i
just sit back and rub my hands okay this
is a bias to be mine for the next couple
of hours and of course to do that you
have to be very level-headed and you
know i don't mind losing the right way
in poker i made the right play I lost
right can I tell story at Jim Ross story
sure so you you gave a great talks it
was about you knows about How to Succeed
in Business head a sort of horrible name
was it called shoot the puppy or
something like that
super puppies ok so ok and so I'm
listening there I'm I'm just an awesome
presentation so fascinating and one of
the stories and correct me if I don't
have this right but one of the stories I
believe you told me is that as a younger
man you you got enthusiastic about
playing poker and learned all about
tells and the mathematics of the game
and so forth and by the evenings you
would play and you know as you got you
know you win some lose some but you got
better and better and you play better
better player
and then eventually I think it was your
uncle pulled you aside said Jim you know
you're smart young man let me let me
give you some advice instead of trying
to play better games just look for easy
games and you know so where your you
know your skills going to be the best
best in that and the group and I just
always loved that and so I actually
wrote a report called looking for easy
games and I started it with a gym rut
you know the whole gym rut story and the
argument is in investing and in business
and anything right if you want to win
one of the things to think about is what
game am I playing and am i they am I
likely to be the smartest guy at the
table I had this really interesting
conversation with Annie Duke the poker
player and she said you know you're a
pro poker player what you do you figure
out kind of your winnings per hour right
so figure out is it worth me plant this
particular table based on how much money
I'm gonna make and being a professional
poker player is not glamorous right it's
just you needs sample size and you have
your button to see for a long time and
so she's playing you know and she's a
obviously a very skilled professional
and she's figuring out her profit per
hour and then she looked to another
table that has lower stakes and she
figures I'm so much better than those
players that my profit per hours higher
at the lower stakes table right I'm
making less per hand but I'm gonna win
many more hands and so she says I'm
gonna allocate some my time to this
other table and so the other poker purse
like what's going or the other people
watching going like what's going on why
is she playing that and she's like it's
just because I'm so much better than
those people I can make more money per
hour I just thought that was fascinating
that's another thing so I talked about
this idea of looking for easy games and
I relate this back to investing for one
moment this is really interesting so one
of the biggest trends in investing as
you know well is this move toward
indexing right so so in the in the last
10 years literally trillions of dollars
have been invested in index funds and
ETFs and so forth and that's largely
been at the expense of active managers
so some people go wow the fact that
everybody's just taking their money away
that means it's going to make it easier
for us active managers less competition
and my response is it may be the exact
opposite and here's the reason investing
as in poker and poker the amount of
money that walks in the room and the
money at the beginning of the night and
the money that walks out of the room at
the end of the night
same amount it's just a different hands
writer in different pockets same is true
for investing right excess returns by
definition net to zero so for you to win
someone else has got to lose right by an
equivalent amount and so my argument is
if it's though weak players who are
leaving the poker table and investing
and putting their money in the index
funds it's like they're showing up your
house on Friday night and they're just
drinking your beer but they're not
putting up any stakes right so you
actually want to have the weak players
at your table for you to may generate
excess returns so part of it is now
you're you're left looking at other
sharp card players around the table and
that actually makes your job harder not
easier so there's a little provocative
thought for you which is is all this
indexing actually making life easier or
harder and if I use the gym rut easy
games framework it may be the case that
my life actually got more difficult not
easier in that you told the story
correctly like add a little corollary to
it we went out to Vegas for my mother's
80th birthday unlike me she loves casino
games to me I just shake my head go and
I'd rather stick my face in the disc
sale there then put a quarter in it slot
machine but I did go down to the poker
room used all my little cunning
strategies I went down at two o'clock in
the morning after having had four hours
of sleep and no alcohol right and I
walked around the poker room and just
assessed each table using my little rule
of thumb that I use and I picked my
table that I wanted to sit down at I
went up to the maitre d and said I'd
like to be on table number seven and he
looked at me and he obviously knew
something and he'd do something that I
knew something and he smirked and said
there's an hour and three quarters wait
for that it was clearly the fishpond
there is no easy arbitrage on that one
it that's not at the Bellagio and as the
end of the World Series approaches let's
let's hop back now from these you know
very interesting stories to a great
tangible story that you tell in the book
which is the difference between finding
drafting I think was the word you used
hunters versus receivers in football
yeah
so there's a great book by cutting Boris
grace Berg called chasing stars and the
the question is and this is also very
it's just a fascinating topic in general
and the question is if you want to
improve the performance of your
organization how do you do that
and one of the logical things is you
look for a star at another organization
and you hire them and they're you know
this halo is going to come over and
improve the value that performance of
your organization as well so Grossberg
studied this in particular it by the way
in finance actually was in analysts and
what he found was that these stars
actually had a substantial degradation
and performance in the new organization
so chasing stars did not work now one
thinks he does not point out which I
would just say is probably a good part
of this is simple regression toward the
mean right which is to say if someone's
a start an organization it's probably
because they've been pretty skillful and
really lucky and if luck is gonna sort
of not persist there's going to be
natural regression toward the mean but I
think the point he makes which i think
is correct
is this idea that there tend to be
organizational externalities that often
people don't take into consideration so
you know if you're a great trader at
goldman sachs there's something about
what's going on at goldman sachs that
makes you very good at what you do and
when you go to you know bank X those
things are not around anymore and hence
you're going to be much less effective
so that's this idea of chasing stars and
by the way there's a really interesting
you know GE and the olden days used to
be known as sort of one of the great
management training places and and goys
burg study there where there was a
couple dozen GE managers who were
considered to be really good and about
half of them went to organizations that
were very much like GE and they did
really well and then half of them went
to organizations that were very
different than GE and they floundered
and so it was not again it's this idea
of organization being really important
so going back to punters and wide
receivers so again how as you want to
make your sports team better how do you
do this and so what their work found was
that wide receivers when they went to
new teams did regress a lot they didn't
do as well as they did on their prior
team now part of this again
I'm sure it's just classic regression
toward the mean but part of this is you
need to learn new schemes you have a new
quarterback all the stuff you have to
sort of move up the learning curve and
you don't have the benefit of all the
stuff you knew at your prior
organization the exception to the rule
though interestingly was punters and
punters were just in Bowie I think I
suspect this true for field goal kickers
as well is that they were the same
everywhere they went and and the point
is that they have very few interaction
effects right you do need a guy to snap
the ball to you but that's basically it
and there are a lot of guys that can
snap the ball you know roughly
equivalent skill and so punting was the
same everywhere they went because that
was the one thing where there are almost
no interaction effects so that sort of
strengthen the overall argument of how
important is the organization to to my
success so that's a really good lesson
in general is this idea of being
skeptical about in quotes hiring stars
as a sure way to lift the performance of
your organization and being
insufficiently mindful of the role in
the externalities organizations and how
they influence people's performance that
that's really useful and now let's move
on to the next item you put somebody who
says the most dangerous equation makes
the equation that states that the
variation of the mean is inversely
proportional to the size of the sample
and again this is something that drives
me crazy in the scientific literature
especially in the biomedical literature
even the most rough calculation says
these people are nuts why are you giving
me results for the sample size of seven
I just don't give a sh it's all noise
right could you talk a little bit about
the importance of sample size yeah and
we'll set in the article I'm because
there's a nice little paper on this by a
statistician at University of
Pennsylvania on this and this is an
incredibly important idea and by the way
it's a it's a snag that's captured some
very smart people all about to tell the
story so this is a key to your point
which is when when sample sizes are
small the variance tends to be large and
this is quite intuitive right which is
if I flip a coin 10 times and it shows
up you know you get 7 out of 10 or heads
or whatever that happens I don't know
something like 12 percent of the time so
that's it doesn't happen frequently but
it's not infrequent as well if I flip a
coin
you know ten thousand times if it's fit
if it comes out fifty-one hundred heads
and 49 under tails that only happens
about two percent time that's gonna
that's very likely to be a biased client
right so we get confused about sample
size and the variance is implied by that
so let me tell you that there's a great
story about how that is snags as some
really smart people so the Gates
Foundation and you know these guys are
doing really really trying to do great
work around the world but the Gates
Foundation want to improve education
United States so there's a pretty
straightforward way to do this let's go
find the schools with a high SSAT scores
right we're gonna look at schools are
really the kids are really doing well
and so they find the kids with a high
safety scores and it turns out these are
small schools now we're gonna come back
to this because you notice they haven't
asked a question another question that
they should have asked and so they go on
a campaign spending millions of dollars
to break up schools to be smaller
because they've deemed them to be more
effective in fact there was a school in
Seattle near Microsoft that they broke
into six little mini schools in order to
take advantage of this idea well what
was the question they didn't ask Jim the
question they didn't ask is which
schools have the worst SAT scores it's
small schools right and because they're
just capturing the tails of the variance
right because of the small sample size
the number of students and so when you
look at the full distribution you start
to see a very different picture and this
idea of small schools in and of itself
is not the correct answer at all and in
fact there and then when you think about
it right larger schools have advantages
like if there are a number of kids that
can take you know fancy AP courses and
you know calculus or whatever it is
you're gonna have a much larger and
larger population of kids it would be
avail themselves of that kind of course
then you wouldn't a small school so
that's just it's a really interesting
thing and I'll just say that
psychologically it's this is really
important is that when you think about
biases that we have we tend to be
overconfident when we see small samples
with strong signals right going back to
my coin toss thing when you see seven
heads and ten tails you start to get
over conference that it's a biased coin
and you don't you don't take into
consideration
the strength of the signal which is
really sample size by contrast when we
have very weak signals like sono they're
my 51% heads with 10,000 tosses but you
have such large sample size we are under
confident that that is biased when in
case a that is very unlikely to be a
biased coin in case B it's very likely
to be bi so that's a really interesting
setup for us psychologically and by the
way Kahneman and Tversky talked about
this in their classic stuff is that we
use small numbers and extrapolate in a
way that's inappropriate so that's an
incredibly important life lesson and
again as you put it out in your setup I
mean you look around the world whether
it's medicine but it's business if you
see all the time that people take small
sample sizes and extrapolate related
concept is recency bias you know you see
the but by the way you see this in crazy
places where people should know better a
baseball player has a great season or
even a great few months before the end
of the season and all of a sudden his
stock goes up and he can sign a more
lucrative contract then he would have
otherwise and it makes no sense but
people fall for this recency bias all
the time so you just really want to
think about sample size and how reliable
are your results in the context of
longer term performance yeah this has
some huge social political implications
and perhaps even world history effects
you know the u.s. we spend 3040 million
dollars at the National Institutes for
health and for various institutionalist
reasons basically because there's a
million biomedical researchers with
their hands out looking for money in the
US we tend to fund maybe barely possibly
adequate sample sizes for biomedical
research but when you add in the noise
from mistakes of experimental design the
reality there's an awful lot of it's
just wrong
for instance god we had on this show
Brian Nozick of the Center for open
science he was also the guy who started
the replication crisis project for
ecology right went try to replicate a
bunch of psychology experiments in top
publications and only about 35% of them
replicated and while in China for
instance in biomedical they have chosen
to take another
approach probably because their number
researchers wasn't is large when they
started doing this is instead of having
a sample size of 40 or 50 they'll have a
sample size of a thousand which means
that they'll do less numbers of studies
but that the value of the information
from each study is much more valuable
and I suspect if the United States could
learn that discipline our large amount
of money spent in federal research would
be better spent yeah I'm with you
hundred percent and these are fairly
basic ideas but remarkably still not
well viscous and incentives and
psychology and so forth but yeah an
institutional bias that's right you got
all them researchers out there with
their hands out and nobody wants to say
no right exactly indeed let's move on to
a couple other interesting kind of
findings that you've talked about in the
book one I thought again it's kind of
informed by all these things we talked
about is what you call the intelligence
quotient versus the rationality quotient
why smart people do dumb things right
I'm personally a fine example by the way
there's another topic I love Jim I just
this is so fascinating to me so this is
work done by a retired professor at
University of Toronto named Keith
Stanovich he wrote a book ten years ago
called what intelligence tests miss and
the core are very provocative claim is
that IQ measure something this is
controversial by the way but it measure
something he claims there's something
real something you know some we can
measure and more of it tends to be
better than less of it but that should
be distinguished from what he calls our
cue rationality quotient which is the
ability to make a decision and again his
core claim is these are only partially
overlapping skills so you might even
think about them as different sliders
and by the way we don't test for our cue
by and large and so his argument is we
all know that's people that do great in
school that really book smart but they
can't make decisions in the real world
very effectively and other people who
are not geniuses but really make good
decisions day and day out so that would
be indications of the differences on the
IQ vs. RQ sliders so this is I think a
really interesting idea and by the way I
think this idea of RQ is really central
to be
certainly a great investor but probably
a great business person as well so he
went out and got a million dollar
Templeton grant to develop what he calls
the comprehensive assessment of rational
thinking cart which is akin to an IQ
test and he wrote a book a couple years
ago about this which laid out
essentially the the skeleton framework
of this comprehensive assessment
rational thinking and it's totally cool
and it is not yet they're still using
only in academic settings but I think
it's an incredibly interesting framework
and you know it tests things like logic
numeracy often people do well don't
believe in things like fate and so forth
so I just think this is a really
interesting area in psychology that will
continue to be explored and I think a
lot of practical implications now I
mention one of the things out as a side
note this is just my belief on this and
by the way I guess it should be more
clear so the key to our cue is is two
things and we'll use some fancy language
right one is instrumental rationality
which is you can achieve your objectives
given your constraints and the classic
way we think about that in economics is
the axioms utility theory but the second
dimension is one much more important
which is epistemic rationality which is
a fancy way of saying your beliefs map
accurately to the world and that's not
easy right because the world changes
right especially in the world of
business or investing the world changes
so one of the keys is to be a good
Bayesian and update your views as the
world changes in front of you so a lot
of this also is things like calibration
that you're well calibrated that when
you say something can happen with a 70%
probability on average it happens 70% of
time so the other link I'll make which I
love is there's a book and I'm a big fan
of both these guys but there's a book by
Phil tetlock called super forecasters
you're probably familiar with it where
they did a forecasting tournament and it
was open and thousands of people
participated and what they found was a
small sliver of that population 2% were
they were so-called super forecasters
and these are people making very good
forecasts that were persistently way
beyond what chance would dictate by the
way they tested obviously for just luck
and they actually asked they some people
in control they gave training others who
didn't but they did they did
personality profiles of all the
forecasters and they created came up
with a sort of a modal sort of mortal
characteristics of a super forecaster
that's gonna circle back to things we
talked about the very beginning these
are people who were actively open-minded
but it turns out I think that the skills
they had overlap almost perfectly with
that of the arc you test right so
they're just people who are willing to
change their mind they're open to new
information and in fact the thing that
correlates best with everything is John
and John Baran's idea of actively
open-minded which means not only willing
to entertain points of view they're
different than what you believe you
actively seek them which by the way
takes a lot of cognitive energy to do
the right I mean most of us just have a
point of view want something once we
decided on it we just want to stick with
what we believe and never change our
view by the way I'll just say I've taken
two when I work out in the in the gym I
often watch television and I now take
into the habit of watching CNN for half
the time and watching Fox News the other
half of the time just to see how the
world works and it's a fascinating
exercise right because people will be
talking about the same topic but but
very different points of view and it's
it is it's definitely I in mind opening
just to see different points of view so
I love this IQ versus rqi I would put
this on the lookout because I think that
this is something that could very well
become more more mainstream and I think
for people it's just a great that's a
great way of thinking about assessing
other people's capabilities beyond just
you went to MIT so you're super smart
guy absolutely and that's something I
learned in the business world relatively
quickly is yes the credentials are
interesting and are useful filter but
don't let them over filter but things I
didn't have the terminology but
something like the RQ is actually more
important in the long run it seems to me
interestingly you mentioned tetlock that
was going to be next up on my questions
and while you talked about what he found
in his super forecasters you didn't
touch on the part that I thought that
was so interesting is that in you know
field after field after field his
research showed that you know most
people for casting behaviors of complex
systems just plain suck at it right it's
a matrix yeah and so I'm
met Phil back probably 2006 or so and he
wrote a book very much for your point
called expert political judgement so
Phil's a psychologist by training he's
now at the University of Pennsylvania
and he but he's very should know he's
been very tuned political science and as
he tells the story it was hanging out
with a bunch of political scientists
back in the 1980s and they're all
pontificating about different things and
he wondered to himself legs anybody have
to keep track what these guys say and
the answer was pretty much no so he
embarked on what end up being a twenty
plus year study of expert forecasts and
is very much viewpoint it was it was
political economic and social outcomes
so these were their sort of canonical
complex systems and these are these are
experts right these are masters PhD
level people and he asked them to make
very specific probabilistic predictions
and they did something very unusual
which is actually kept track of them and
the results are very much what you
described is they're very bad at this in
fact you know simple extrapolation
algorithms tend to do as well or better
and very many of them don't do it much
better than chance the other thing I'll
just remark about these experts is
they're just like you and me when they
get something wrong and they have all
litany of excuses as to why they they
got it wrong you know I you know you
just wait or or I almost got that right
my favorites used by the way it was my
forecast was so important to change the
car too often but um but this is this
actually an important point that and I
think this you know we had that
symposium on complexity economics a
couple of weeks ago testify and I think
that many of these kinds of questions
about expertise for instance really are
incredibly domain-specific and so there
are areas where experts actually are
really good and they tend to agree in
fact in my book think twice I have a
chapter called the expert squeeze and I
discuss where experts are likely to
continue to be important and where
they're not and so look if you have a
tricky math problem or or you need your
plumbing fix or something you know there
are going to be expert you can call them
that can do that and the results are
going to be consistent with one another
and they're gonna agree for the most
part but when you get into complex
systems as you point out predicting
markets or oil prices or geopolitical
outcomes it's it's a bit of it's the
complex systems Wild West and there you
will find experts as you as you point
out equally credentialed who will come
up with diametrically opposite
conclusions you know oil prices are
going to sky
oil prices gonna plummet and there we
know their track records really poor so
part of part of my thing is to say and
and by the way the other thing I'll just
say that we know psychologically we'd
love to defer to experts you know why do
we have the Talking Heads on CNBC every
days cuz those people are really we'd
love to listen to them and we love to
think that they know what they're
talking about right so there's there's
something enduring about our desire to
listen to the fortune teller to some
degree so my whole thing is be super
sensitive to the domain that you're
thinking about and to recognize and in
some domains experts are absolutely
going to be great and they're gonna be
useful and you're gonna want to defer to
them but you can't extrapolate the
abilities in some domains and into the
complex systems world because it just
doesn't work and and again your mind is
gonna want to believe but you should
suspend that and and that belief and
recognize that no one knows what the
heck is going on so so tight locks work
I think the first thing was and but
unbowed I think he's a very thoughtful
guy so even even there were some silver
linings and in the original work on
expert political judgment but to
recognize that there are very few
experts that can predict well now I will
say one thing Jim this goes also back to
our conversation about the Santa Fe
Institute I thought one of the most
remarkable there are two remarkable
things that were in Ted Locke's findings
that were significant one was I love
this the more media mentions a pundit
had the worst his or her predictions
were one way the people you hear and see
the most frequently are though worse
when you actually objectively keep track
of their record now part of that is
because if you're in the media so you're
a producer for a TV show or you're an
editor of a newspaper you kind of want
to have people to have kind of crazy
views of the world right you want boom
stirs and do stirs to be on your your
talk show in order to generate interest
but the second thing he found was that
what predicted success of forecasting
had less to do with your gender or age
or political persuasion and much more
with your way of thinking so he
hearkened back to the famous Isaiah
Berlin essay on foxes vs. hedgehogs so
hedgehogs are those people that know one
big thing and pretty much anything you
chuck at them they're gonna pound into
their worldview one way or another we
all know the sort of
and the other the contrast is the foxes
or these are people know a little bit
about a lot of different things they
tend to hold their views lightly and
their constant learners and they tend
not to be too wedded to any particular
point of view and and I think for me at
least I think that SFI tends to be the
kind of place that draws foxes which is
always super fun and what tetlock found
was hedgehogs will have their 15 minutes
of fame so if your boom stir or doom
stir and the market goes up a lot or
down a lot you're gonna you're going to
be in the spotlight for a moment but
over time it's the foxes it tend to be
better forecasters because they're more
malleable cognitively malleable and so
as new information comes in they'll
actually update their views in both the
direction and magnitude that makes sense
so I love all that stuff I think it's
really important again I think
temperamentally some some people are
better at it than others but all these
things and I should have said this about
our queue I think it's actually quite
difficult to change people's IQs that
much but but there are some I think
reasonably convincing evidence that that
our queue something you can cultivate
both as an individual and even as an
organization and this idea being Foxy's
also something you probably can
cultivate as an individual and that's
that sort of an encouraging note right
at the end that this is really difficult
but we can probably do better than we're
doing indeed let's go on to another
topic and this is something at one level
once I read it and thought about it said
sure of course that's intuitively
obvious but it's an idea I had never
come across before I think it'd be very
useful for people to add to their
intellectual toolkits and that is that
you point out and give some examples
that when skill starts to converge in a
domain luck actually becomes more
important because you knock that a
little bit Jim these are all the most
fun topics yeah so this is I want to say
that I learned this originally from
Stephen Jay Gould who wrote a book
called full house in the mid-1990s and
in the end full house is really about
this idea of distributions I gave it the
name the paradox of skill but I want to
be very clear that I got that idea from
Gould and I'm sure Gould may have gotten
this from someone else
and just to rephrase what you just said
the idea the core idea is that in
activities we're both skill and luck
contribute to outcomes which is most
things of course that it can be this
case that a skill increases luck becomes
more important and that seems like a
really weird finding and the key insight
to this and as you said once you explain
it it becomes extremely intuitive the
key insight is you have to think about
skill in two dimensions the first
dimension is absolute skill and I think
that we would all agree if you look
around the world whether it's business
or sports or investing or anything the
level of absolute skills never been
higher than it is today what which by
the way you would expect because of
cumulative human knowledge and
technology and so on and so forth so you
know to be concrete if I put you as an
investor if I put you back in the 1960s
with the tools at your fingertips today
you could run circles around your
competition right you'd simply have
better information faster trading and so
on so forth and we see this by the way
in sports especially things measured
versus a clock as we know right you know
people are constantly setting records
for the fastest running time or swimming
time or what have you
the second dimension though is where it
gets super interesting and that is
relative skill which is the difference
between the very best and the average
now Gould introduced this idea with a
story about Ted Williams Ted Williams
was last baseball player to hit over 400
for a season he did that in 1941 and he
hit 406 and gules asked any question
like why is no one hit over 400 since
1941 and he's like certainly that
players today are better than they were
before they trained better that better
nutrition they better coaching and so
forth and his argument was at the end of
the day it turns out that they're more
uniformly excellent and as a consequence
that standard deviation of skill has
gone down so to say this slightly
differently and a little bit more
technically you can think about batting
averages as a normal distribution the
mean is usually around 260 you know
something like that and by the way the
powers at major league baseball will
actually change the rules
have cheese rules over the decades to
make sure that there's no advantage
going to the pictures of the hitters
right so 260 and then you can calculate
the standard deviation of that around
that mean and so it turns out that Ted
Williams was almost exactly a for
standard deviation event in 1941 right
which is extremely rare and you would
just say a lot of luck and a lot of
skill right there's no other way to get
there without lot bund ins of both of
those things now in the most recent see
oh I didn't do 2019 but 2018 season if
you were a for standard deviation hitter
which would be spectacular you would hit
something like 385 something like that
right which is awesome that wins the
batting title hands down but you don't
have come near breaching the 400 level
and the reason is because the standard
deviation of batting average has gone
down over time so the difference between
the best player and the average player
is is less today than it was in prior
generations and you could test this in a
bunch of other ways as well go look at
the gold silver bronze winners and the
marathon or the 100-meter dash and the
Olympics going overtime and what you'll
find is that those guys are a lot closer
today than they were in prior
generations so you know we see in
basically parity in athletics in general
if you look at sports leagues and B NB
is not a good example hockey NFL
baseball they're all grindings or parody
part of is because there are things like
salary caps and so forth but the bigger
phenomenon is just we're drawing from
larger populations of potential players
we train them better we coach them
better they eat better as a consequence
excellence has become more uniform which
is really interesting perhaps where this
is the most powerful is in the world of
investing and investing this area where
the cumulative knowledge of everybody
goes into asset prices and wondering as
we track as the standard deviation of
excess returns and that has been
marching steadily lower through for the
last 50 years by the way there was one
market departure from that trend and
that was around the dot-com period and
interestingly the dot-com period is when
mom-and-pop came back into the stock
market
droves and that setup and this goes back
to your discussion about easy games that
set up a situation where there was skill
versus non skill and it turns out that
the institution's ended up fleecing
mom-and-pop who then retreated after the
dot-com thing busted and then the
standard deviation of skill went right
back to trend of shrinking over time
isn't that a fascinating thing so this
idea the paradox of skill and and once
you hear about this idea and sort of
internalize the basic framework and look
around you see this everywhere where
again absolute skill never higher
relative skill shrinking and luck
becoming more and more important in
determining outcomes that the takeaway
is even more reason to look for the easy
game right that's really an overarching
thesis and all this is that if you have
skill or you have if you believe you
have differential skill you want to
figure out where to apply it and that's
a really big deal and I think people
don't think enough about that and right
that was that's why I think that any
Duke story stuck with me so much it was
you know people thought she had you know
sort of lost it that she was going to
play in the lower stakes table but she
was doing a cold heart calculation of
profit per hour and that ended up being
the best place to be so super
interesting because had a couple other
things here before we're out of time you
had a section on that people lose skill
with ages but so do organizations so
what can you tell us about that hahaha
so there's a little bit depressing but
um but it turns out that what I try to
do in two chapters one on luck and one
on skill is to sort of characterize what
they look like and you know
characterizing skill is actually not
that difficult to do and we can even do
it by talking which is skill tends to
follow an arc and then athletics is a
good way to illustrate this but we can
talk about lots of other stuff as well
so let's say you're an athlete when
you're young you're obviously not very
skilled you're not very strong and you
improve improve improve through practice
and strengthening and maturation so
forth and then you peak at some level
and then you come down the other side so
and by the way different pro sports the
peak age of performance varies a little
bit but it's usually somewhere in the
mid 20s to 230 something like that so
that's usually the age of peak athletic
performance and then there's a
degradation so
older athletes tend not to perform as
well and by the way that you know a lot
of it is just basic plumbing that as you
get older you just your reaction times
just slow just a tiny bit and of course
when you're a professional athlete for
instance those those things actually
make a huge difference in how you
perform by the way the same is true in
cognitive performance you know one of
the theories on this is your general
intelligence function of your
crystallized and fluid intelligence
crystallized intelligence exactly what
it sounds like it's your understanding
facts and knowledge and so forth that
tends to grow through life and absent
you know sort of any kind of cognitive
impairment that tends to grow until
you're you know well into your 70s but
fluid intelligence which is your ability
to deal with novelty tends to peak when
you're young actually in your early 20s
and declines over time so you have these
countervailing forces of crystallize
going up in fluid going down and that
also creates an arc which is interesting
and then you mention organizations and
we see the same type of thing is that
organization performance tends to also
follow an arc that's harder to quantify
but as you know when you're you're young
and you tend to be filled with sense of
purpose you tend to be more nimble and
then as you get larger you just become
more more bureaucratic part of us out of
necessity and so one of the ways we can
track that things like return on capital
patterns and organizations and companies
so return on capital tends to start low
as you're getting going and you're in
sort of an investment phase then tends
to grow and then you get to a peak and
then you come down reflecting both
maturation typically of the markets in
which you're participating and also sort
of the bureaucracy that tends to almost
inevitably grow within your own
organization yeah so that tends to be
the pattern so that's always thing to
think about is where is a company where
as an individual on that pattern of
skill on day on the ascend are they on
the descent and what does that mean for
for the future that might be a wonderful
little tool for doing and best min
analysis right say all right here are
the tells that let me know this company
is past its prime yeah we actually Jim
we actually do some work on that and
what we typically do is look at is
basically the degradation you call it
the fate of return on capital over time
and so if you have you have a high
return on capital business how
quickly will that regress back towards
some sort of opportunity cost and one
things that the empirical work will tell
you which which is it's going to be very
intuitive when I say this which is that
differs by industry and sector right to
state the obvious and so things like
energy and parts of financial services
tend to have very rapid regression right
because it's easy for people to mimic
what you're doing and it's often a
commodity type of business and so
replication is easy and so those returns
get competed away quite quickly by
contrast other businesses you know the
sort of classic examples consumer
staples is that you know you probably
use Proctor and Gamble products 30 years
ago and you'll probably use them 30
years from now those things tend to be
much more stable as a consequence the
fades tend to be a little bit slower so
you're right so a part of it is just
understanding what those curves look
like and also recognizing that those
will vary by industry you know
justifiably so yeah you like you wrote
about that and I fact I even wrote about
it the only thing I ever wrote under SF
i's name was talking about where to
think about exploration and exploitation
right some people you know say oh there
should be some you know set mix wrong it
very much depends on the environment
you're in if you're operating a pittin
factory you're probably all about
exploitation if you're working on in the
Internet industry in 1998 you're
probably all about exploration it's very
important to get those things straight I
don't want to reread your paper Jim
because I want to I also want to come
back to that topic I think that's an
first of all what you said it's spot-on
and it's an absolutely fascinating
concept and then the question is you
know can you sit in at a board meeting
or talk to a CEO and actually articulate
this in a way that's that they can
really get them thinking about it and it
goes back to what you're talking about
institutional bias and inertia and all
these kinds of things it becomes really
difficult and at least perceived
expectations of the financial community
it becomes very difficult for these guys
they sort of paint themselves in a
corner and overdo it on one side or the
other well we got time for one last item
before we have to run out and I'll give
you your choice I've got lots of topics
which we did not get to that your book
was just such a mine of interesting
things but give you a choice of which of
the leads you want to exit on one
earnings per share why is it
shitty measure or second this would
probably be my preference term I did not
know so I read your book was it was
deliberative practice you mentioned it
many times throughout the book and you
actually spent a fair amount of time
late in the book describing it in some
detail let's start with the latter in
you know that on deliberate practice and
I think this is um this goes back to a
skill in skill acquisition and even
spills into this whole discussion about
10,000 hours so by the way it SFI we
have a really fascinating program on
limits you know this well so limits to
all sorts of limits to knowledge limits
to performance and so forth and we did a
conference a couple years ago on limits
of human performance and you know we had
everywhere from you know talking about
athletic performance we had special
forces folks we had neuroscientist and
so forth but one of the guys that sort
of kicked off our discussion with ended
was Anders Ericsson who was the guy
whose most famous for the discussion
about 10,000 hours and what Erickson
argues I'm gonna make this a little bit
of a cartoon version of it but I don't
think it's that far off what Erickson
argues is this idea of talent or skill
doesn't really matter what matters is
you apply yourself for 10,000 hours of
practice and you will become elite in
that particular activity so if you Jim
rut want to get to Carnegie Hall playing
the violin it's just 10,000 hours of
deliberate practice and we're gonna get
you there right now I think anybody in
the real world recognizes that the
notion that there's no talent or skill
doesn't make any sense right so we all
know people have musical abilities or
mathematical abilities or language
abilities and so forth we're athletic
abilities so I just think that the point
is a bit of a non-starter but this idea
of a deliberate practice I think is
really important and by the way the
other thing I'll just say there's a
great book called a sports gene by David
Epstein David's a great guy his new book
by the way also I love called range I
would highly recommend that it's a very
also very SFI type of thing where it's
an argument about specialist versus
generalist the argues very I think
persuasively in favor of generalists but
in the sports gene David dismisses this
idea and shows empirically this idea of
10,000 hours is not really true that's
maybe an average but this idea of
deliberate practice is valid so what is
deliberate practice it just says if you
want to get better at something
and this is this comes from Anders
Ericsson you want to do what's called
deliberate practice which is operating
at the edge of your capabilities you're
getting very accurate and timely
feedback typically from a coach and it's
actually not fun so it's easy to apply
to some things like sports right your
your tennis player and you and and you
you practice every day at the edge of
your performance you have a coach giving
you timely and accurate feedback and
it's hard work right and and also there
are components that you need rest and so
forth and how those things fit into that
and so the idea is that most of us don't
actually ever get to the point of
deliberate practice on most things right
so if you want to learn to drive your
car you know you get to you get to be
competent at it and you'll leave it
there so good enough for most things is
good enough but to truly become
outstanding at something especially in a
fairly defined domain you need this idea
of deliberate practice so one things I
and we could even muse about this
together gym right now which is this
idea of if that's a valid construct for
how to get really good at something what
is the equivalent of deliberate practice
in business so you're gonna coach an
executive like how do you coach that
that individual so that he or she can
actually become more skillful in
investing what is deliberate practice
mean and investing right investing is an
inherently noisy exercise as a
consequence it's very difficult to give
people clean feedback your business is
very noisy hard to get people clean
feedback right so that's a really
interesting open question which is are
there methods or techniques that we
could use to get more effective at
prescribing deliberate practice and
domains that are not again very tidy
where the feedback is clear and so forth
so I think is I think it's an incredibly
interesting topic and it gets into
things like how do we train how do we
you know NSF I we did a little fun
session on agent based models and part
of the the power of agent based models
is it allows you to expand your mind and
understand how certain causes and
effects come out of these simple little
models it just changes the way you think
about things and I think that whole idea
of deliberate practice is another really
cool area that we could
explore do your question about you know
in business as you know I do a little
CEO coaching from time to time and what
I have decided for my CEO coaching which
is the closest thing to this idea of
deliberative practice that I can think
of in my own experience is I focus
relentlessly on time management right
and Ty instantly is a client management
that sounds boring as but in
reality I've concluded the time
management is really how we
operationalize our priorities and our
priorities are critical but writing your
priorities on the whiteboard is one
thing actually living them is another so
whenever I'm doing a CEO coach and thing
I start off with a priorities exercise
and then I do a time management exercise
seemingly separate and then I point out
the contradictions to the person I'm
coaching and then I provide a
prescription on how they should approach
their time management and I give them
things like take this piece of paper
that you just created and tape it to
your computer so you see it several
times a day and think of time management
as the deliberative practice you have to
force yourself to do against your own
inclinations and likes and dislikes if
you're going to actually achieve the
priorities that you really care about
see I love that and I'll just mention
you know this is completely related
which is there was a really interesting
survey of investment committees these
are you know down nents and pension
funds and so forth making investment
decisions and they asked the each member
of the investment committee what should
we be doing and rank these things in
order right and then they actually kept
track of what they actually did and they
were almost flipped to lists right and
so it's the same thing it's like time
management like why are we spending on
time on things we shouldn't be spending
time on and why are we not spending time
on the things we should be spending time
on but it goes back to a little bit you
know part of the challenge I'm sure you
see this even in your CEO coaching which
is some of the challenges sometimes you
make the right decision now you get your
time priorities correct right sometimes
you make a decision which is the right
decision that doesn't work out and
that's where you have to say to people
you did the right thing dust yourself
off and go do it again tomorrow right
and sometimes you make a dumb decision
it works out and you go wait a second
like recognize that you were just got
you're just completely
on this next time think about it more
effectively right so that's that's also
this idea of giving people you know sort
of see through the outcomes and saying
like let's make sure you're focused on
the proper process and I think that's
another area that could really be
helpful to get people to continue to
focus on process as it means to the
long-term outcomes successful long term
outcomes in fact I do exactly that
that's one of the advantages I have
having had a zillion years of business
experience with a large number of
businesses as I have I've said both of
those things definitely which is okay
you failed but you failed honorably and
intentionally and next time that comes
up do the same thing ie view the same
process and over time you will be a
winner and on the other hand I
definitely have told people Jesus Christ
did you luck out right won't do that
again because probably next time you're
gonna fall on your ass ah well anyway
Michael we're at the month the hour and
thirty minute mark and I found that's
about as long as I can do a good job and
I'm sure you could go on for hours but I
have to keep my focus up too and I
frankly looking at the statistics I
think that's about as long as our
audience can tolerate but as I expected
this has been intense interesting
valuable and all those kinds of things
that we're trying to achieve here well
thank you so much your most real blast
and we did talk about a lot of really
fun topics and hopefully useful topics
for people out there in the real world
yep and people don't forget to buy
Michael's book why don't you give me
your the title the success equation easy
to find anywhere amazon.com is good
place to go definitely read it I've had
it very worthwhile production services
and audio editing by Jared Jane's
consulting music by Tom Muller at modern
space music com